A Guide to the Trilateral Commission (North America) records FA420
Rockefeller Archive Center
The Trilateral Commission (North America) records
1972-2001
Rockefeller Archive Center
The Trilateral Commission (North America)
FA420
167.02 Cubic Feet 373 letter document boxes, 12 legal boxes, 15 record storage boxes.
Total volume is an approximation.
Biographical/Historical note
The Trilateral Commission is a discussion group focused mainly on policy studies which was founded in 1973 by David Rockefeller and several other prominent private sector leaders of North America, Europe and Japan to broaden the understanding of international issues and their transnational impact.
In many ways the origins of the Trilateral Commission stem from the reorganization and reconstruction of the political and economic order following the resolution of World War II. The United Nations Monetary and Financial Conference held July 1-22, 1944 at the Washington Hotel in Bretton Woods, New Hampshire, commonly known as the Bretton Woods Conference, brought together delegates from all the allied nations to stabilize and regulate the international monetary and financial order. The Bretton Woods accords established the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) and the International Monetary Fund (IMF). A period of significant economic growth followed particularly in the regions of Western Europe and Japan where the redevelopment of infrastructure and the expansion of trade exports increased their relative economic power.
The exchange rate management system established at Bretton Woods, with the U.S. dollar as its benchmark, remained in place until 1971 when U.S. President Richard M. Nixon abolished the direct convertibility of the U.S. dollar to gold and in effect abandoned U.S. participation in the Bretton Woods system. In this period of rapid change, economic and financial instability and growing nationalist tendencies discouraging the open market system established at Bretton Woods, the Trilateral Commission was conceptualized and formulated.
In March 1972, speaking before Chase Bank investment forums in Montreal, London, Brussels and Paris, David Rockefeller called for "an international commission for peace and prosperity composed of private citizens drawn from the NATO countries and Japan to examine such vital fields as international trade and investment; environmental problems; control of crime and drugs; population control; and assistance to developing nations."1 Rockefeller considered Japan as an essential member of the international community and viewed a commission as a mechanism for including the Japanese in the international dialogue.
While on an airplane headed to the Bilderberg group meeting in Belgium in April 1972, David Rockefeller spoke with a like-minded colleague Zbigniew Brzezinski, Director of the Research Institute on Communist Affairs, Columbia University. Two years earlier Brzezinski had published Between Two Ages: America's Role in the Technotronic Era in which he advocated that "a community of developed nations must eventually be formed if the world is to respond effectively to the increasingly serious crisis that in different ways now threatens both the advanced world and the Third World."2 To address transnational issues and problems "an effort must be made to forge a community of the developed nations that would embrace the Atlantic States, the more advanced European communist states and Japan. These nations need not – and for a very long time could not – form a homogenous community resembling EEC."3 Brzezinski's thesis called for reshaping the framework of international affairs. "Movement toward such a community will in all probability require two broad and overlapping phases. The first of these would involve the forging of community links among the United States, Western Europe and Japan, as well as other more advanced countries...the second phase would include the extension of these links to more advanced communist countries."4 Brzezinski envisioned forming a trilateral body, "a high-level consultative council for global cooperation, regularly bringing together the heads of governments of the developed world to discuss their common political security, educational-scientific and economic-technological problems, as well as to deal with their moral obligations toward the developing nations."5 Finally Brzezinski argued that a trilateral body intent on enabling international discourse and the sharing of information regarding issues of commonality is lacking within the existing structure of international organizations, stating that "a council of this sort, perhaps initially linking only the United States, Japan and Western Europe, and thus bringing together the political leaders of states sharing certain common aspirations and problems of modernity, would be more effective in developing common programs then is the United Nations, whose efficiency is unavoidably limited by the Cold War and northsouth divisions"6
The Bilderberg group promotes understanding and discourse between North American and Western European countries. At the April 1972 meeting David Rockefeller, as he had done previously, urged the Bilderberg Executive Committee to take a trilateral approach and invite the participation of Japan. When his recommendation for trilateralism was again rejected by Bilderberg, Rockefeller continued to pursue the idea, investigating its application through further consultations with Brzezinski, George S. Franklin, a college roommate of Rockefeller's at Harvard who served as Executive Director of the Council on Foreign Relations from 1953-1971, and interested colleagues in Europe and Japan. David Rockefeller's consultations culminated with a July 23-24, 1972 meeting at Pocantico Hills, NY attended by C. Fred Bersten, Robert Bowie, Zbigniew Brzezinski, McGeorge Bundy, Karl Carstens, Guido Colonna di Paliano, Francois Duchene, Rene Folk, George S. Franklin, Max Kohnstamm, Bayless Manning, Kiichi Miyazawa, Kinhide Mushakoji, Saburo Okita, Henry Owen, David Rockefeller and Tadashi Yamamoto; in which the participants enthusiastically agreed to take steps to establish the Trilateral Commission.7
Shortly thereafter in the Fall of 1972 and early 1973, the respective areas designated regional chairman, Zbignew Brzezinski was selected as the Commission's Director, and financial support was obtained from several sources including but not limited to the Kettering Foundation and Ford Foundation, to supplement the initial seed monies provided by David Rockefeller.
The Commission was originally established for a 3 year period. It has since been renewed for successive triennia, most recently for a 13th triennium to be completed in 2012.
1 Rockefeller, David. Memoirs. New York: Random House, 2002, p.416. 2 Brzezinski, Zbigniew. Between Two Ages. New York: The Viking Press, 1970, p.293. 3 Brzezinski, Zbigniew. Between Two Ages. New York: The Viking Press, 1970, p.295. 4 Brzezinski, Zbigniew. Between Two Ages. New York: The Viking Press, 1970, p.296. 5 Brzezinski, Zbigniew. Between Two Ages. New York: The Viking Press, 1970, p.297. 6 Brzezinski, Zbigniew. Between Two Ages. New York: The Viking Press, 1970, p.297. 7 The Trilateral Commission: A Proposal, March 15, 1973, folder 6062, box 997, RG 3. Rockefeller Brothers Fund Records, RAC.
Biographical/Historical note
Administrative Structure of the Trilateral Commission
Organizing Chairman (Founder) – David Rockefeller
Regional Chairmen – Three (One from each trilateral region)
Director – In the first triennia, the Commission had a central Director, Zbigniew Brzezinski, responsible for overseeing day to day operations, focusing particularly on policy studies.
Coordinator – In 1977, the Commission chose to decentralize by creating the position of Coordinator rather than continuing with a Director. The Coordinator, George Franklin, was chosen by the Executive Committee. The Coordinator continued to oversee Commission operations, but the European and Japanese offices were considerably strengthened.
Executive Committee – comprised of Regional Chairmen, Deputy Chairmen and other members from all three regions. The Executive Committee is responsible for the policy recommendations of the Commission.
In 2000, the Commission accomplished one of the goals Brzezinski had envisioned by expanding its membership to include representatives from other advanced democratic nations – restructuring the Japanese membership to encompass that of the Pacific Asian region including but not limited to: Australia, Malaysia, New Zealand, Philippines,Singapore and Thailand. Commission leaders have also actively sought to include individuals from communist and other non-trilateral countries in the discourse, through the planning for, and/or holding of meetings in non-trilateral areas such as Moscow (1980), Beijing (1981) and Mexico City (1984, 1990). Such meetings were not always successfully held as initially proposed, but the Commission continues to engage opportunities to enhance the discussion through expanded participation and the inclusion of differing perspectives.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Microfilm copies of portions of the Zbigniew Brzezinski Files (Box 241A), Gerard C. Smith Files (Box 308B-P), and Trilateral Commission Early Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 310A-B) are available at the Jimmy Carter Library, Atlanta, GA.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Trilateral Commission (North America) donated these records to the Rockefeller Archive Center in March 2003. The Archive Center received the collection in four accessions in 1985 (Accession 1985:153, 1985:171, 1985:201) and 2002 (2002:045).
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 15 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
To be granted access to the records of the Trilateral Commission (North America), all users must complete an RAC use agreement. Please see the RAC Head of Reference for details.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents note
The objective of the Trilateral Commission is to foster discussion and cooperation among the core democratic industrialized areas of the world. David Rockefeller defined the Commission's primary focus as bringing "the best brains in the world to bear on the problems of the future."8
In the 1970's the dominance of the United States in the world community and economy was diminishing and there was a sense that a new more equitable paradigm of international affairs would be needed to address global challenges. The Commission acts as a platform for greater cooperation between the member regions as well as an opportunity to enhance discussion and understanding of the problems, concerns and interests common to all three areas.
Upon its founding in 1973, the Commission's immediate goals were to introduce Japan into the international community; welcome Japanese participation in trilateral discourse; and bring together prominent non-governmental leaders, representing all three geographical regions and a variety of professional fields to address the key common problems facing the three regions.
Specific aims of the Commission include:
1. To facilitate better communication. Communication in turn helps to alleviate potential misunderstandings as well as to develop greater understanding of the complex issues confronting the three regions and the world.
2. To propose policies. Policy recommendations are mainly in the area of foreign policy including economic relations, political and security concerns, and the relationship of trilateral countries to the developing world and/or to communist nations.
3. To foster understanding and support of the Commission's recommendations among governmental and private sector non-member leaders in all three trilateral regions.
Files for the regional commissions in Europe and Japan are not represented in the collection.
8 Sklar, Holly ed., Trilateralism. South End Press, Boston, MA., 1980. p.83.
Related Archival Materials note
1. Rockefeller Brothers Fund records, Grants. 2. Rockefeller Family & Associates, General Files. 3. John Stremlau Papers, Box 26, Folders 301-303. 4. Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs Series Files document Rockefeller family contributions to international relations including the Institute of Pacific Relations and the Council on Foreign Relations.
Nuclear disarmament; Nuclear arms control; International relations; International economic relations; Energy policy; Environmental policy; Asia -- Foreign relations; East-West trade; Industrial relations; International cooperation; Fiscal policy; Foreign relations; Nuclear energy; Asia -- Foreign economic relations -- United States; Population policy
- Meetings, 1972-2001; 1; 42.06 Cubic Feet 90 letter document boxes and 6 record storage boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The collection does not contain documentation of the European or Japanese/Pacific Asian Executive Committee meetings.
  The Commission serves as a forum for discussion of issues common to all three trilateral regions, primarily by organizing and holding meetings among and between its members.
  Arrangement
  Series 1 is arranged into the following subseries: 1. Preliminary and Early Meetings; 2. Principal International Meetings; 3. Other Meetings. Each subseries is loosely arranged chronologically. Subseries 3 is primarily arranged by meeting type, and subsequently loosely arranged chronologically.
  Other Finding Aids
  For an overview of meeting records contained in the collection, please refer to "Major Meetings" (available as a PDF)
  Related Materials
  Documentation of various Commission meetings is also available in the Francois Sauzey files in Series 3, the Officers Files (Series 5), and the Early Office Files in Series 6.
  1. Preliminary and Early Meetings, 1972-1975 The preliminary and early meeting records document several preparatory meetings in the Commission's formation. Files are also included from North American regional meetings which preceded the international Executive Committee meetings in 1973 and 1974. The pattern of meetings in the early years was for the international Executive Committee meeting to be preceded by regional meetings of the entire membership in that given region.
  2. Principal International Meetings The principal international meeting records provide documentation of the Executive Committee meetings, Plenary meetings, and the preparation for several meetings planned to be held outside the Trilateral area including Moscow early 1980 (a planned meeting with members from all three regions - cancelled after the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan); Beijing 1981 (a meeting held in 1981 with members from all three areas, followed by travel in China); and Mexico City 1984 (cancelled due to scheduling when it became clear that President de la Madrid would be out of the country at the time). A conference was later held in Mexico City prior to the 1990 Plenary meeting in Washington, D.C.
  Since the inception of the Commission, the location of the annual meetings has rotated among the three regions.
  The first three international meetings of the Commission --- 1. Tokyo October 1973; 2. Brussels June 1974; and 3. Washington, D.C. December 1974 --- were all executive committee meetings. The first international plenary meeting was held in Tokyo/Kyoto in May 1975. The next major meeting was an executive committee meeting held in Paris in December 1975. Then the May 1976 meeting in Ottawa was a plenary meeting. All subsequent principal international meetings have been plenary meetings.
  From 1976-1979 the plenary meetings took place approximately every 9 months. Since 1979, the plenary meetings have been conducted on an annual basis. The substance of the principal international meetings is collected in issues of Trialogue, (which draws together presentations from each meeting) and through the project reports (which are discussed in draft form at the meetings). Meeting participation and programs can be tracked in the program/bio books.
  3. Other Meetings The records of other meetings include that of: Chairmen's Meetings, 1974-1998 (typically held just prior to the annual plenary meeting, although in some years they were held directly after the plenary meeting); Three Region Executive Committee (typically met over breakfast on one day of the plenary meeting.); North American Executive Committee and Trustees (typically met each summer and have held some special meetings); Meetings with David Rockefeller as Chairman; North American Events; North American Regional Dinners, 1986-1991 and European Regional Meetings. Documentation of various Commission meetings is also available in the Francois Sauzey files in Series 3, the Officers Files (Series 5), and the Early Office Files in Series 6.
  - Preliminary and Early Meetings, 1.1
    - International Commission on Peace and Prosperity - George S. Franklin, Pocantico, 1972 July 23-24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meeting - Minutes, 1972 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Visit to Europe Re: Proposed International Commission, (Max Kohnstam), 1972 May 23-June 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Comments on Proposed Commission, 1972 May 23-June 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Meeting - Agenda, 1972 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Meeting - Master Copy of Proposed Agenda, 1972 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Persons Interviewed In Europe, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Visit to Japan (with David Rockefeller and Joseph V. Reed, Jr.), 1972 June (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Expenses in Connection with Project, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Meeting - Agenda (New), Pocantico, 1972 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Meeting - Agenda (Old), Pocantico, 1972 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Meeting - Minutes, Pocantico, 1972 July 23-24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meeting - Participants, Pocantico, 1972 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - North American Commissioners Meeting, (Includes Report), 1973 October (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Papers from Messrs. Bowie, Brzezinski, Colonna, Franklin, Kohnstamm, Owen (with Originals) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Meeting - Joseph Veneer Reed, Jr., Pocantico, 1972 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Meeting - George Franklin, Pocantico, 1972 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Luncheon Conversation About the Trilateral Commission, 1972 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Planning Committee Meeting, 1972 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Meeting, Minutes, Paris, 1972 October 25 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Japan Trip, 1973 January 8 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Meeting - Minutes, Geneva, 1972 November 25 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1972 December 23 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Planning Committee Meeting, Washington, D.C. - Henry Owen's Place, 1972 December 8 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Meeting, Brussels, 1961 July (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Meeting, Atlanta, 1973 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Meeting, Washington, D.C.., 1973 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Meeting, 1973 September 16 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Meetings, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28A)
    - U.S. Commission, 1973 October 15-16 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Meetings, Tokyo, 1973 October (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Carnegie Endowment, 1973 December 13 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Meetings, Washington, D.C., 1973 December (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Chairmen's Meetings, London, 1974 May 17-18 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Commissioners Meetings - Master Attendance List, 1974 May 29-30 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - North American Commission Meetings, New York, 1974 May 29-30 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - North American Commission Meetings, New York, 1974 May 29-30 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - North American Commission Meetings - Notebook Contents, New York, 1974 May 29-30; 3 copies. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - North American Commission Meetings, 1975 October (Box 3, Folder 37A)
  - Principal International Meetings, 1.2
    - Principal Trilateral Commission Meetings, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Executive Committee Meeting, Tokyo, 1973 October 22-23 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Report [written in English and Japanese], Tokyo, 1973 October 22; 2 copies (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Declaration for Executive Committee, Tokyo, 1973 October (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Program, Tokyo, 1973 October 22-23 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Executive Committee Meeting, Brussels, 1974 June (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Executive Committee Meeting, Brussels, 1974 June 23-25 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Joint Statement, Brussels, 1974 June 23-25 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Master Attendance Sheet, Brussels, 1974 June 23-25 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Notebook, Washington, D.C., 1974 December 8-10; 2 copies. (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Participants, Washington, D.C., 1974 December 8-10 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Miscellaneous, Washington, D.C., 1974 December 8-10 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Kissinger Dinner, 1974 December 9 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Speeches, Washington, D.C., 1974 December 8 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Hara, Shonfield, Roosa - Inflation (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Summaries, Washington, D.C., 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Executive Row Hotels, Washington, D.C., 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - International Club Meeting, 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Executive Committee Resolution - Draft and Final, 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Executive Committee Welcome Letter, 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Program Schedule, Washington, D.C., 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Embassy Row Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Responses, 1974 December 8-10 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Executive Committee, Dinner Invitations, Press, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Kissinger Dinner, 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Joint Statement, 1974 December (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Executive Committee - Expenses, 1974 December (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - President Ford Meeting, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Papers, 1974 December (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Executive Committee Meeting - Participants, 1974 December (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Remarks by George W. Ball, 1974 December 8 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Executive Committee, Fall 1974, 1974 December 8-10 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Executive Committee, 1975 Fall (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Meetings, Program Options, etc., Japan, 1975 May (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Meetings - Responses, Japan, 1975 May (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Meetings - Non-Commissioner, Company Representatives, Japan, 1975 May (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Joint Statement - Kyoto, 1966 July 25-27 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Euro-Japanese Meeting, 1975 May (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Japan - Foundation Invitations, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Japan Plenary Meeting - Industrial Practices in Japan, 1975 May (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - Haggerty Remarks, Kyoto, 1975 May (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Japan Plenary Meeting - Bills, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Japan Plenary Meeting - Speeches - Schroeder, Kashiwagi & Watanabe, Kyoto, 1975 May (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Plenary Meeting - Program [written in English and Japanese], Kyoto, 1975 May; 2 copies (Box 7, Folder 81)